<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://dopieralski.pl/</id>
  <title>dopieralski.pl - Posts in lifehack</title>
  <updated>2026-01-10T22:16:51.302876+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/"/>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/blog/category/lifehack/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2019-03-26-boredom/</id>
    <title>Boredom</title>
    <updated>2019-03-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="boredom"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would you like to be more creative? More eloquent in conversations? More
intelligent in decision making? Better at problem solving? More attentive? Able
to read those difficult books? Focus deeply on the project at hand? There is a
simple solution for all this: embrace boredom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes some effort and training, but I can assure you that it certainly is
worth it. Whenever you are waiting, whenever you don’t have anything urgent to
do, whenever you don’t particularly feel like doing something, just be bored.
Forget about taking out your phone and mindlessly scrolling through the social
network stream, frantically checking your messages, or playing silly games
designed to get you addicted to them. Just stay there and think about whatever
comes to your mind: that conversation you had last week with a friend about
morality, that book you are reading, that project you were planning to start,
what you will tell the person you are waiting for when they arrive, what you
will do next, etc. — it doesn’t really matter what you think about, just let
your mind wander.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of this? You will have more motivation to actually work on that
project, you will understand the book better, you will have interesting things
to say in the next conversation, you will enjoy your time with that person
more, and so on. Because your mind will have done some of the work up front and
will be prepared. Because you will also think about things that you wouldn’t
notice otherwise. Because you will be more rested and ready to pay more
attention to the here and now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is not a silver bullet. It doesn’t work when you are tired,
depressed, stressed and burned out: you have to make sure you take care of your
sleep deprivation, depression and anxiety first — don’t be afraid to talk to a
doctor about them, they are often very easily cured. But once you have that
under control, make sure to leave yourself as much time as possible for doing
absolutely nothing. Literally staring at a wall. It will make everything else
you do much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2019-03-26-boredom/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Would you like to be more creative? More eloquent in conversations? More
intelligent in decision making? Better at problem solving? More attentive? Able
to read those difficult books? Focus deeply on the project at hand? There is a
simple solution for all this: embrace boredom.</summary>
    <published>2019-03-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
