<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://dopieralski.pl/</id>
  <title>dopieralski.pl - Posts in automation</title>
  <updated>2026-01-11T08:40:51.228772+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/"/>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/blog/category/automation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-07-01-automation/</id>
    <title>The Subtle Art of Automation</title>
    <updated>2025-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="the-subtle-art-of-automation"&gt;

&lt;section id="tools"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans are tool-using animals. For a long time it was thought that this is what
distinguishes us from animals, in fact, but of course if you actually pay
attention you will notice that animals are using tools all the time. Yes,
sometimes you can dismiss it as instinctive behavior, as is the fashion, but
sometimes when it comes to corvids, parrots, octopuses and primates, you really
have to admit that they do it intentionally and with full knowledge about the
expected results. Anyways, humans are among tool-using animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we use tools? Sometimes it’s because we are not strong or dexterous
enough to do thing we want to do unaided. Or our nails and teeth are not sharp
enough. Or our sight, hearing, or sense of touch are not good enough. Other
times we could do the thing unaided if we had to, but tools make it easier or
more convenient. Sometimes it’s because we don’t want to risk an injury, or to
get dirty, or we want to avoid other unpleasant sensation. But the reason I
hear given most often is that by using tools we can do the same thing faster,
or at larger scale, or otherwise more efficiently. We can achieve the same (or better) result with less effort. Tools can be a labour-saving device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We say “tools”, but it’s not just tools. They are just easy to talk about them,
because they are tangible, visible things. But it all applies to skills and
techniques as well. To the “technologies”. Consider, for example, waving
baskets. It’s something you do by hand (today we do have machines that can do
it, but let’s assume we are doing it by hand), but you can do it in several
different ways. Coming up with a new way to wave baskets that is somehow
easier, faster, lets you use different materials or produces baskets with
special qualities that the other ways don’t works exactly the same as if you
created a new tool for doing this. So tools are just physical manifestations
of technologies, and it’s the technologies we will be concerned about here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="effort"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Effort&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So do the technologies really save effort? It certainly feels that way, why
would we be using them otherwise? But I think it’s a bit more complicated than
that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the ox-driven plough. On the face of it, it’s a huge improvement about
the humble hoe that it replaced. Yes, the farmer still has to be present to
drive the plough, and it still requires a lot of strength, but a large amount
of that strength is now provided by the animal, and the whole work goes much
faster. So it’s a definitely a huge saving, at least as long as you only look
at this short time when the ploughing is actually happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the ox has to eat too. And it needs a place to stay, and it needs to be
taken care of. And when it gets old or sick, it has to be replaced. So for this
to work in the long run you need a steady supply of oxen. (And I’m not even
saying anything about the effort of the ox.) So a tiny plot of land that acted
as the farmer’s garden and was enough to feed their family now has to become a
considerably sized field, enough to grow food for a herd of oxen and the people
needed to take care of them. And since the oxen need to eat the entire year,
you have to store your crops somehow, and preserve them.  What used to be a
simple shack with a small garden, where some hoe-ing would happen a few times a
year, turns into a small village with several huts, a barn, an enclosure, and
people working around the clock to maintain all that. And don’t even get me
started about fresh water and the smell of ox everywhere. And of course because
you are not storing considerable caches of food, your little village is now
vulnerable to raids and looting (or the more civilized version of it,
taxation), so you need defensive walls, soldiers (or at least militia),
weapons, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at it this way you could easily conclude that the hoe is in fact the
less labor-intensive solution, when considered globally. It only becomes worse
when you assume that you already have all the infrastructure need for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then again, once you have the infrastructure, it enables not just the
plough, but many other technologies as well. You now have milk and meat. And as
much ox shit as you can shake a stick at. You have fortifications and army.
You have a hierarchy to organize and manage it all. You have surplus food to
trade. And so on and so forth. So assuming you want all those additional things
too, on top of replacing the hoe, the plough once again becomes the superior
technology (for some chosen measure).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="transformers"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transformers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if technologies don’t &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; save effort on their own, what do they do
exactly? I like to think of them as transforming one kind of effort into
another kind, potentially better suited for the task at hand, or maybe just
easier to store or move around. If you compare the rather abstract and nebulous
idea of effort to thermodynamic idea of energy, a technology could be like,
say, a solar cell that transforms light into electricity that can be then
easily moved around using wires and stored using batteries. Or a combustion
engine that transforms chemical energy of the fossil fuels into kinetic energy
of a rotating shaft. Of course the similarity is pretty weak, because we don’t
really have a well defined formal theory of effort, like we have a theory of
thermodynamics, but I like to believe that there is some kind of law of
conservation of effort somewhere in there, however fuzzy and approximate it
might be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, technologies let you transform different kinds of effort,
sometimes allowing you to store or move it around. What good is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out that sometimes some kinds of effort are better for a given task
than other kinds. So you can “save effort” by using the kind that is more
efficient for the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And sometimes certain tasks take less effort when they are done at a particular
place and time, or when they are done at scale. Being able to store and move
effort lets you rearrange it into more efficient ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, sometimes you can “outsource” the effort, by taking advantage of
something someone else already did (or will have to do to clean up after you).
Fossil fuels, for example, take advantage of the effort the plants of millions
of years ago spent to turn light into their bodies, and of the effort the
future generations will have to spend to deal with the climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like in thermodynamics, those conversions rarely are free – usually they
take some additional effort, to, say, dig up those fossil fuels, turn them into
a form that is convenient to use, and transport them to the right place. But
with the right arrangements, even with that overhead we can often create
considerable savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="automation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Automation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automation technologies (together with mechanization) are no different in that
regard, except they tend to require much more infrastructure to make things
happen “on their own”. They also come with a myth that “you only need to set it
up once” and they will work forever without expending any further effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice any ongoing process is going to have setup cost and maintenance
cost (and also cleanup cost, which we often forget about). In addition, the
requirements for the output of the process are going to change over time, and
that requires further effort and resources to adjust it to remain useful
(either by changing the process itself, or by adding extra adapting steps).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the trick is to setup that automation in a way that minimizes those ongoing
costs, possibly doing more work up front, or pushing more work to the cleanup
(and hoping we won’t be around anymore when it happens). This is not a given,
and if it’s not done intentionally, we might as well end up with an automated
process that doesn’t in fact save effort, or accomplish other goals that we
wanted to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="goals"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of goals, saving effort is not the only thing technologies can give
us. In fact, sometimes we are ready to actually spend more effort in order to
achieve some of the other goals. What are they? Potentially they are infinite,
but let’s look at some of the most common ones here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="repeatability"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Repeatability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be a goal to have multiple similar things, or it can be just enabling
the further goals like quality control or fine tuning, but automation sure lets
you do things the same exact way, if setup with that in mind. As a side effect,
it also makes it easier to debug!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="quality-control"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Quality Control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to make sure that the things you are making are at least of a certain
quality. But maybe you also want to make sure that the quality is not
unnecessarily high, as it usually costs more. If your process is automated,
then you can easily inspect it, find the parts that have the most impact on
quality and adjust and monitor them. You can even automate additional quality
checks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="fine-tuning"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fine Tuning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait, it’s not just quality. You can fiddle with any feature of the process
this way. The fact that it always happens the same way, except for the parts
you have changed, lets you more easily see what the results of your changes
are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="interchangeability"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Interchangeability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you design your automation right, you can reuse or share parts of it in
different processes. You could also have intermediate stages of the product
shared between several different processes. This lets you both save effort and
be more flexible about your quotas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="scalability"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Scalability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you make a machine do something, then you can often quite easily run the
machine faster, or buy several machines and have them run in parallel. You can
scale your processes this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="economy-of-scale"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Economy of Scale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you can scale something, you can scale it up to huge amounts and make use
of all those bulk discounts and bulk shipping. More importantly, you can use
bigger machines to make the same thing faster and cheaper by making a lot at a
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="centralization"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Centralization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously if you have big machines doing a lot of work, you want them all in
one place, so that you can keep all the resources and materials close by,
and so that the maintenance is easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="distribution"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Distribution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you don’t have to centralize everything if you don’t want to. Automation
also enables distribution, letting you to have the same machine (or script)
running in many different locations, close to where they are needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, automation can be quite useful and universal tool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where am I going with this? My main point is that automation is not always
about saving effort, and that it doesn’t automatically save effort wherever it
is used. Sometimes it has other goals, and sometimes it actually makes you
spend more effort, especially when you count all the effort that is normally
not visible, because it hides in the infrastructure or has been pushed out onto
the customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, there are certain patterns and arrangements that you can use with
automation tools that work well for achieving a given goal. And there are also
anti-patterns that make automation pointless or even harmful. The trick is in
knowing what you want to do and how to arrange things to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-07-01-automation/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Humans are tool-using animals. For a long time it was thought that this is what
distinguishes us from animals, in fact, but of course if you actually pay
attention you will notice that animals are using tools all the time. Yes,
sometimes you can dismiss it as instinctive behavior, as is the fashion, but
sometimes when it comes to corvids, parrots, octopuses and primates, you really
have to admit that they do it intentionally and with full knowledge about the
expected results. Anyways, humans are among tool-using animals.</summary>
    <published>2025-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
