<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://dopieralski.pl/</id>
  <title>dopieralski.pl - Posted in 2026</title>
  <updated>2026-01-11T08:36:51.548260+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/"/>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/blog/2026/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2026-01-11-circuitpython/</id>
    <title>CircuitPython in 2026</title>
    <updated>2026-01-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="circuitpython-in-2026"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that time when the CircuitPython project is looking for feedback from the
users, so here is some of mine again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been mostly focused on three projects using CircuitPython last year: my
&lt;cite&gt;quadruped robots &amp;lt;https://deshipu.art/projects/project-188909/&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt;, the &lt;cite&gt;PewPew
game console &amp;lt;https://deshipu.art/projects/project-185291/&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt;, and the &lt;cite&gt;µGame
game console &amp;lt;https://deshipu.art/projects/project-178061/&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt;.  I didn’t have
much energy to do any serious progress on any one of them, but I did some
experimenting, and I have some ideas for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I failed in my attempts to port the speech synthesis engine from MicroBit to
CircuitPython as a C module, but &lt;cite&gt;someone ported the project
&amp;lt;https://github.com/jacklinquan/micropython-samtts&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt; it is based on (the SAM,
Software Automatic Mouth) to plain Python code, and it runs on CircuitPython,
albeit the format conversions necessary to subsequently play it using
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;audioio&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; make it somewhat slow. Unfortunately, the non-repeat playback of
&lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;RawSample&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; is currently pretty broken in CircuitPython, so even though I did
get this to work, it’s not really usable until those bugs introduced later
changes are fixed. I took a stab at one of them, but I’m not really familiar
with that code enough to know what it was supposed to be doing in the first
place. In any case, there is a way to do voice synthesis in CircuitPython now,
which is nice for things like talking robots. We can hope the audio libraries
will become more stable in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have given up on working on a touch version of the &lt;code class="docutils literal notranslate"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;keypad&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; module for the
SAMD21 port. The main problem is that those registers are completely
undocumented, because Microchip sells a commercial library that uses them, and
prefers for everyone to use that. Adafruit worked around that with their
current CircuitPython code, but without access to the same documentation, I
have little chance. Having that module would greatly improve the functioning
of those PewPew devices that use touchpads for the buttons – right now the
code is polling them, which is slow and unresponsive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also looked at using different chip than the hard to obtain SAMD21 for
the PewPew devices, in particular the &lt;cite&gt;CH32V208
&amp;lt;https://www.wch-ic.com/products/CH32V208.html&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt; looks very promising. It has
64kB of RAM, 128kB of Flash, and clock up to 144MHz, which should be sufficient
for CircuitPython running simple games of the PewPew. The problem is, of
course, that there is currently no port of CircuitPython to that chip. I looked
a bit into what would be involved into making such a port, and I will probably
give it a go at some point, but the task is somewhat daunting and certainly
requires more energy than I have at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I’m finalizing the hardware for the ESP32-S3 version of the µGame
handheld game console. You can think about it as &lt;cite&gt;Adafruit PyBadge
&amp;lt;https://www.adafruit.com/product/4200&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt;, but with larger screen, and more RAM
and Flash. And somewhat better looking, in my opinion.  There are no changes in
CircuitPython necessary for it, except for the board definition, which I will
submit once I’m sure about the hardware, and once I get a USB pid for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the near future, I want to focus more on writing new games for
CircuitPython, in particular, I really want to make a roguelike game for that
platform, as I don’t think there is one yet. It feels to me like I should do
the hardware work first, the put off the fun of making the games, but the
reality is that a game console without games is a pretty boring thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the CircuitPython project itself, I think it’s in a good place in terms
of functionality. Yes, better async support and fewer bugs would be nice, but
there really isn’t anything that stops me from doing the things I want to do
with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2026-01-11-circuitpython/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>It’s that time when the CircuitPython project is looking for feedback from the
users, so here is some of mine again.</summary>
    <published>2026-01-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
