<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://dopieralski.pl/</id>
  <title>dopieralski.pl - Posts in gamedev</title>
  <updated>2026-01-10T22:16:51.293642+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/"/>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/blog/category/gamedev/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2020-06-21-snowball/</id>
    <title>Progress Mechanics</title>
    <updated>2020-06-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="progress-mechanics"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress is an important mechanic in computer games. Not only it gives us a
reason to play the game, but it also serves as a way of communicating how
well we are playing. It can also serve several other purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="reward-spiral"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reward Spiral&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most obvious ways of implementing progress is to simply reward the
player with experience points, better equipment, or other resources as they
complete fragments of the game. Defeating opponents, completing quests,
arriving in a new area, finding hidden treasures, etc. can all be used for this
purpose. However, there is a danger in this if the rewards are useful in terms
of the gameplay mechanics – they make the game easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making the game easier as the player progresses is bad in single-player games
because it often makes the game boring – the initial challenge, when finally
overcome, becomes a mindless grind to get more of the rewards, with little
actual skill required. To counter that, game designers will often try to offset
player progress with stronger monsters and harder levels – so that even though
the player character gets more powerful, so do the obstacles. This results in a
kind of a power inflation phenomenon. It requires careful balancing, because a
small random fluctuation can leave the player facing unrealistic challenges, or
catapult them into too easy a game, staying just ahead of the difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While bad in single-player games, in competitive multi-player games this
mechanic is often devastating. Whichever player manages to get even a tiny
advantage, through skill or luck, gets catapulted ahead of the other players,
and leaves them in the dust with no hope of winning, except maybe for a
desperate gamble to get ahead in the initial stages. You can see that in action
particularly well in the board game Monopoly, which was actually designed to
demonstrate the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="optimal-tactics"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimal Tactics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When playing a game in which rewards make the game easier, there is no longer a
dilemma between sharpening your axe or cutting the tree. When you have to
choose between gaining more power or doing something useful, you always have to
choose more power. Anybody who diverts even a tiny bit of their gains into
something else than immediate growth will fall back on the growth curve behind
their opponents and lose the game. Power is the only thing worth fighting for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game is won or lost in the initial stages. Your best tactic is to optimize
for short-time advantages, keeping yourself alive and as close to the point
where the exponential growth begins, in the hope that a random fluctuation will
boost you onto the path to victory. Sometimes you might even be able to see the
fluctuation coming, or even to arrange it to happen, but there is still an
element of randomness here, as some other player might be better positioned to
exploit it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your gamble worked and you get catapulted, all the other players will try
to latch onto you, surf the same wave as you, or simply shoot you down to give
themselves another chance. This is a delicate moment when you have to
ruthlessly attack anyone who comes close to you or tries to overtake you. Exponential growth will exaggerate any initial differences fast, so all you have to do is to make sure you are leading for a short time, and afterwards you will be pretty much outside the reach of the other players. You have won the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game could end at this point, but usually it doesn’t. The exponential
growth means that the differences between players grow, and it’s pretty much
impossible to change their order anymore. The growing powers will now compete
for resources, until all are consumed, and then they will start eating each
other, with the stronger taking over the weaker. In theory it’s still possible
for two weaker powers to combine and overcome a stronger power, but in practice
the stronger power can prevent that from happening by defeating one of the
weaker ones before they merge. The game turns into a boring grind, desperate
struggle to survive as long as possible and push away the inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is no time limit, the game will always end with one player controlling
all the resources, standing on the burned husk of the world, with nothing more
left to conquer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="politics"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Politics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this looks to you like a criticism of capitalism, it’s probably because
there are similar mechanisms at play. Bringing it all down to money (or
capital, or power, or whatever single resource) does this. I’m not an economist
or a politician, so I’m not going to dwell on this too much. I’m sure you can
find such discussions easily elsewhere. I’m going to get back to game design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="breaking-the-loop"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Breaking the Loop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see that this kind of positive feedback loop, where getting more powerful
lets you easier become even more powerful is harmful to enjoyment of games. So
what can be done to fix this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious thing you can do is to separate the “victory points” that you
gain for completing elements of the game from the other in-game resources. Make
it “fame” or “status” or distance travelled or whatever else that has no direct
impact on the ease of playing. Don’t worry, humans have an intrinsic desire to
make numbers go up, and they will care about that number even if it doesn’t do
anything. In multi-player games you can say that whoever has the most of those
points after a certain time, or whoever reaches a certain number first, wins.
This works very well in games like Splendor, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can do even better. Make the victory points a burden. Make the game
&lt;em&gt;harder&lt;/em&gt; for the players that have more victory points. There are several
interesting ways to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a card game Dominion, you build your deck as the game progresses. Victory
points are scored by buying cards that have victory points on them – but
usually those cards don’t do anything else, they just take up space in your
deck, and remove the opportunity to play cards that actually bring you
advantages. If you start by buying victory cards from the beginning, you will
soon have a deck that is almost entirely victory cards and you won’t be able to
do anything, soon your treasure cards will become so rare in the mass of
victory cards, that you won’t even be able to buy the cheapest victory cards.
So instead you have to balance your game carefully between buying the treasures
that let you buy better cards, the actions that let you interact with your deck
and other players to play better cards, and the actual victory cards. And that
balance depends very much on what the other players are doing. This makes the
game massively more interesting, and lets all players to play at their own
pace according to their own strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting trick is to leave the power inflation in there, but subtly
use it to make the game more complex as it progresses. You can see that for
example in the computer game Doom. The weakest weapon in the game needs no
ammunition and no aiming – you just come up to the monster and punch it. But
as the monsters become more powerful you have to use more powerful weapons, at
the cost of complexity. The second least powerful weapon, pistol, requires
ammunition and works at a distance, so you can’t just hold down the fire button
and run around, you have to conserve your resources and aim. The next weapon, a
shotgun, adds a long delay after each shot, so careful aiming becomes even more
important. This pattern continues, with every weapon adding some kind of a
special challenge – whether it’s especially rare ammunition, rocket explosions
that can hurt you, a spin-up delay before the chain gun starts shooting, or
long delays before and after each shot. As a result, power inflation prevents
the game from becoming easier, and the growing complexity of the stronger
weapons makes the game more interesting as it progresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="fungibility"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fungibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We say that something is “fungible”, when it can be easily exchanged into other
resources. A lot of things are fungible in the modern world, because gives us
more options and frees us from having to plan too much – there are people who
live owning just a few things (and a big bank account), because they can always
buy whatever they need, and discard it afterwards. But this also means it’s
much easier to fall into a power loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social status used to be divorced from money or capital. People scoffed at the
“nouveau riche” – people who have become rich recently, but don’t really have
high social status. Master artists and craftsmen used to be rather poor and
often relied on patronage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today things have changed. A rich person can become a famous innovator by just
buying a car factory or a space rocket business. Status is decided by the lists
of the richest people published by magazines. And money also give you access to
the politicians, so you can make sure the rules won’t change. Fungibility has
created a positive feedback loop of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can it be avoided? Of course. You just need “victory points” separated from the
money. Have goals that can’t be bought: being a good member of your community,
having friends, learning skills, performing an art, protecting something
irreplaceable, creating something unique. Separate different parts of life, so
that being successful in one doesn’t automatically make all the others easier.
And most importantly, noblesse oblige – make the game harder for those with
more victory points – expect more of them in exchange for the power they
wield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s worth to pay attention to what progress mechanics you have in your game
and how they affect the feel of the game and the incentive of the players.
Many techniques and tricks can be adapted, both from other games, and from
the wider world of economics, politics and social sciences in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2020-06-21-snowball/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Progress is an important mechanic in computer games. Not only it gives us a
reason to play the game, but it also serves as a way of communicating how
well we are playing. It can also serve several other purposes.</summary>
    <published>2020-06-21T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
