<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>http://dopieralski.pl/</id>
  <title>dopieralski.pl - Posted in 2025</title>
  <updated>2026-01-11T08:36:51.550337+00:00</updated>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/"/>
  <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/blog/2025/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://ablog.readthedocs.org/" version="0.10.33">ABlog</generator>
  <entry>
    <id>http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-05-09-politics/</id>
    <title>Political and Practical Worldviews</title>
    <updated>2025-05-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="political-and-practical-worldviews"&gt;

&lt;section id="slavic-gods"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Slavic Gods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we were somewhat brutally brought into the loving embrace of the Roman
Catholic Church by our considerate neighbours, my country had its own “pagan”
religion, with its own mythology and traditions. A lot of the traditions
survive in some way, because you can’t tell people they no longer have
a holiday on a given day just because they are worshipping a different god
now, but most information about the beliefs of my ancestors have been
judiciously eradicated by the same people who were at the time responsible for
preserving history – the chroniclers were mostly priests at the time, after
all. Some of it has been reconstructed from mentions in various historical
texts, but there is very little that is certain. Which is a great shame,
because those “primitive” mythologies often were records of knowledge about
the world and its workings, presented in a form that is easy for people to
understand – attitudes and relationships. That’s why gods in them are mostly
humans with special powers connected with the nature. And that “pagan”
mythology could tell us a lot about how the society functioned back then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, one particularly well attested god (possibly because it was easy
to compare with similar Greek, Roman and Nordic gods) was the god of thunder
named Perun. He controlled the weather and could send storms and control the
lightning. His symbol was an oak tree (because those trees were often hit by
lightnings), and he was said to live on tops of the mountains. He generally
fits the Proto-Indo-European pattern of a storm god. He was also the god of
warriors and battle, and he would punish dishonorable behavior with death in
battle. He was worshipped by warriors and nobility, and his temples and
statues would often stand on tops of hills, inside city walls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some sources indicate that Perun had a competing god that is, unfortunately,
not as well attested. His name was Veles, and he was the god of cattle,
craftsmen, and science (well, magic and secret knowledge, but that’s how it
worked back then). His statues would stand outside the city walls, in the
village in the valley. He was said to live underground, and to take care of
the souls of dead people. He would punish breaking of contracts with
a disease. He was worshipped by what we would today call “upper-middle class”
– various craftsmen, artists, shepherds and cowherds, smiths, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, there are literally only a handful sources mentioning Veles by
name, and historians mostly reconstructed him from stories that survived to
the modern times with the gods replaced by saints. In particular, the story of
Saint George killing a dragon seems to be such a remnant. It’s another pattern
that repeats all over the Proto-Indo-Europen mythology. The story is rather
simple: there is a drought, and Perun discovers it’s caused by Veles in the
form of a giant snake blocking the water at the source. So he challenges him
to a fight, which is visible to the people as a storm, with lightning bolts
hitting the giant snake. Veles avoids defeat using various tricks, but
eventually escapes and hides, releasing the water, which then falls from the
sky in the form of rain. Prosperity returns until the next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some historians insist that this is supposed to explain the seasons, but I’m
doubtful. I think this story tells us about a different social mechanic, one
that is much more important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="systems-of-survival"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Systems of Survival&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I stumbled into a small book written by the famous architect and
urbanist Jane Jacobs, titled “Systems of Survival”. Unlike her other books,
it’s not about cities, or economy, or urban planning. It’s about morality.
Specifically, it’s about morals in professional settings. In that book she
identifies two “moral syndromes”, as she calls them – two ways of looking at
the world and deciding what is good and what is bad. The two ways are both
consistent internally, but often conflict with each other. She named them
“commercial” and “guardian” (she initially wanted to call it “raider”, but
realized how intimately it is connected with protecting territory). She notes
that a lot of morally questionable worldviews come from mixing elements from
those two systems, creating internally inconsistent “monstrous” systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also notes that in the modern world it’s impossible to survive sticking to
only one of those worldviews. We have to switch between them depending on the
context, using the commercial syndrome in trade, science, and technology, and
the guardian syndrome in bureaucracy, politics, and public services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to read the book if you can, or at least look at the Wikipedia
summary of it. It made a huge impression on me, because at the time I was
investigating a different duality I noticed in my profession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="wizards-and-warlocks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wizards and Warlocks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a software engineer. I maintain and develop software for a living. That
means that I spend a lot of time thinking about programming, and also talk to
other people about it. I couldn’t help but notice that most arguments in the
programming practice are between two distinct styles of reasoning about
computer programs. When I looked at it closer, I decided to call the people
promoting those styles “Wizards” and “Warlocks”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wizards really appreciate the effort of writing code that is correct,
performant, and generally elegant. They care about the code itself very much.
They want to understand it all, and to have full control over every aspect of
it. Even if they include some dependency, it’s only after they have reviewed
it, and possibly even forked and modified it to better match what they expect.
They tend to work on relatively small, but high quality projects. They also
tend to stick to a single programming language of choice for the given
project, and are not afraid of adding things to it if they are required for
their task. They tend to stick to a single project at a time, and get back to
it to gradually improve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warlocks just want to get things done. If there is a library or framework that
already does most of what they need, they are happy to use it. They will copy
snippets of code from random websites, and even use code generation tools. If
they are missing something in one language or framework, they don’t mind
changing to another one that has it, or creating a hybrid solution that uses
both. They usually don’t much care for formal correctness, performance, or any
kind of aesthetics in what they cobble together. They just want it to do the
thing they need good enough for their needs, and they don’t really care how it
is done under the hood. They also don’t come back to old code, unless they
have to fix something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course in real life nobody is fully a wizard or a warlock. You have to
switch between the two approaches as needed. Sometimes practicality beats
purity, sometimes technical debt is unacceptable and needs to be minimized.
Sometimes you want to move fast and break things, and sometimes you want to
move slowly and fix them. Knowing when to use which style is an important
part of being a software engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t mean there aren’t biases. In fact, most people prefer one style
of work over the other. There are even programming languages and other tools
that specifically encourage one of those styles over the other. While you pick
them depending on the context, there is always room for interpretation, and
arguments, and often you will see the same people fall consistently on either
side of those arguments. Some people simply prefer to be wizards or warlocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="dualities"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dualities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to find opposing dualities. Good and evil, light and dark, order and
chaos, female and male – as soon as we can think about it, we can split it
into two opposing states. But most of those a gradients. There are few
dualities where we can see the two opposing sides, but nothing in between.
For instance, there are visual tricks, like the Necker cube, where we can
interpret the same picture in two completely different ways, but not both at
once. Which interpretation we choose depends on a complex mixture of visual
hints, lighting, situational context, and personal preference. But we can also
consciously force ourselves to see it one way or the other, if we want to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moral syndromes identified by Jane Jacobs seem to be like that. Once you
decide on one feature – for example that it is good to do mutually beneficial
trade – all the rest jumps in place: the need for honesty and contracts, the
universal rights, shunning of force, thriftiness, etc. It’s all or nothing. If
you cherry-pick features from both moral syndromes, you inevitably get an
inconsistent mixture that is morally questionable. And just like with the
Necker cube, we seem to naturally pick the syndrome to use based on subtle
hints, situation, and preference. For example, if the matter at hand is
related to territory of some kind, we tend to pick the guardian moral
syndrome. But I think they are also kinda sticky – once we decide to use one
and not the other in a given situation, we will tend to repeat that choice
again in a similar situation, unless we consciously decide otherwise, or
something happens to change our minds. So as we go through our lives, we
collect examples of situations and assign them one or the other moral
syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="more-than-a-syndrome"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More than a Syndrome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane Jacobs called her findings “syndromes”, because to her that is what it
was – literally groups of symptoms. In her book she made observations about
them, but she refrained from jumping to any conclusions, or speculating about
the mechanism that creates them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t have to be so restrained ourselves. In fact, I’m now going to make
wild generalizations and come to crazy conclusions without so much as a shred
of proof or research. I’m going to do it because it’s fun, and because I think
it’s useful to imagine what we &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; find there if we took the time to look
closer and do proper research. You can think of it like a science fiction book
about how alien civilizations could look like – it might be inspired by our
existing knowledge, but most of it is just fantasy and speculation. Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s stop calling them “syndromes” and give them a more representative
name: worldviews. Also, I’m not very fond of the names “guardian” and
“commercial”. I understand where they came from, but I don’t like the
connotations they bring to mind. Let’s call them “political worldview” or
“political thinking” and “practical worldview” or “practical thinking”, and
let’s call the people who predominantly use one or the other “politicians” and
“builders”. It will shortly become clear why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="relationship-with-truth"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relationship with Truth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every politician knows intimately that truth is always negotiable. It’s
a consensus. You can get away with the most outrageous claims, as long as
you make them confidently, and other people are inclined to let them slide,
usually because objecting would be very inconvenient for them. This is why
they will always try to color the truth to their advantage, and they don’t
even consider this to be lying. And they will also always assume that other
people are doing it all the time as well. Or should be doing it, and it’s
only their own fault if they are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The builders can’t afford to bend truth. They usually work where the rubber
hits the asphalt, and the physical reality doesn’t care about how strongly you
believe something or how convincing you are. You are either right (or close
enough) and things work, or you aren’t, and they fail spectacularly.  Besides,
physical truths are out there for everyone to see. Unless it’s a high energy
physics problem, you can usually do a simple experiment that will easily show
you if you are right or not. Even with high energy physics the experiments can
be replicated and confirmed. So it simply doesn’t make sense to lie about
those things, or even to hide them, because they are in the open for everyone
to see. And finally, unlike with politicians who always assume you are lying
anyways, and who are completely unsurprised when you are caught lying, the
builders care a lot about maintaining trust, and a single lie can ruin your
reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This points to another clue that can be used to decide which worldview to
choose in a given situation: when you are building something, doing scientific
research, planning a trip, or even just cooking, you are better off with the
practical worldview, because it lets you learn from mistakes and improve your
technique, until it works. On the other hand, if you are trying to get a
building permit, doing humanist research, telling a bed time story to your kid,
or organizing a party, you will probably be better off with political thinking,
as the success depends more on other people agreeing with you than on actual
physical reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="communication-and-trust"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Communication and Trust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Builders trust strangers implicitly, at least with low-risk things. With more
successful interactions that trust increases, and everyone builds
a reputation. They also treat all promises seriously, and feel very hurt when
a promise is broken. Even if it’s for something insignificant, it can break
your reputation. Builders will also often communicate without words, by just
doing things and having others decide how to best cooperate with them, if they
want to. This is somewhat similar to what is called stigmergy in ants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politicians never trust other people, because they assume that everybody are
lying all the time anyways. This poses a problem, because you need a certain
amount of trust to cooperate in a society. There are generally two commonly
used solutions for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you can put some “skin in the game” to show that you really mean what
you are saying. This can be anything that costs you, like a charity donation, a
lavish party, generous gifts or bribes, but often also comes down to violence
or threats of violence. To a politician, nothing underlines your point better
than a brutal attack to get the other party’s attention. Even if the goal is
alliance, this is not malicious, this is just a way they communicate. You can
think about it like an elementary school student trying to get the attention of
a person they like in their class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second way to get some semblance of trust, is to get a third party to
guarantee the agreement, usually by threatening sanctions if it is broken.
This is why politicians love authorities of all kinds – they make it easier
for them to trust each other. Even if the authority in question is corrupt
itself, to a politician it seems better than just trusting the word of the
other side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practical mindset is also at odds with censorship. If you can see the
truth from the world around you, it makes little sense to control what people
talk about. Political mindset regards control of the flow of information as
very important. After all, it doesn’t really matter how things actually are,
but only what people believe they are. If you can control what people believe,
you can control reality. This especially shows in how people approach
scientific publications: the builders will trust the publications that were
detailed and can be reproduced experimentally. Thew politicians will trust the
publications published by authoritative organisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="justice-and-force"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Justice and Force&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the use of force. As you can guess, builders hate violence,
and generally only use it for self-defence (though the definition of
self-defence can be overly board sometimes). They will hesitantly acknowledge
the need for violence sometimes, but they will not want to have anything to do
with it themselves. It’s distasteful and uncomfortable. Ideally, all conflicts
should be resolved peacefully, and the guilty parties should submit willfully
to whatever punishment (usually in the form of recompense) is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Builders believe that the world should be fair, and everybody should start out
with equal rights and opportunities. Some of them will act as if that was
actually true, and fall for the just-world fallacy. Things not being fair is
a big problem for them, and they will work to fix such perceived flaws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The politicians don’t mind violence at all, and they will use it casually just
as a way of amplifying their words. They put fundamental human rights in the
same category as the tooth fairy and Santa Claus – it’s obviously false, but
it’s rude to say it aloud, because some children still believe it and it’s
cute. The world belongs to the powerful, and if you can’t defend your
property, then it never was yours in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a dog-eat-dog world, and the only way to survive is to be stronger than
the others. Justice is all about demonstrating your power by retaliating, so
punishment have to be public, often over the top, and it doesn’t really matter
if they person being punished is actually guilty. It’s all about demonstrating
what happens to those who step out of line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="work-and-ownership"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Work and Ownership&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the builders, your success is comes from the work you do, risks you take,
and deals you make. Everything you have you either earned by working, or
traded for something else you earned (or traded, and so on). Everybody work
together for the common benefit, and make the world a little bit more
convenient and safe. The things you were given don’t really count. Your value
is based on your skill, industry, and entrepreneurship. You become better by
learning skills, acquiring tools, and cooperating and competing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the politicians, your success is your fate. You are a chosen one, destined
for greatness, and your rights and obligations come directly from who you are.
You prove your greatness by defeating others. When you get defeated yourself,
it’s so that you become stronger and more ruthless. The world is a zero-sum
game, and the only way to grow is by taking from others. And you deserve to
grow, because you are the destined future of all of humanity, who will perish
without your leadership. Or something along those lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work is something dirty to politicians. They are aware that it’s somehow
happening somewhere, but they don’t talk about it, and don’t understand it.
Value comes from owning things: land, factories, subscription services, mines,
data centers, patents, copyrights, stock shares, capital, etc. – owning them
makes you entitled to the resources they produce. Some of them produce more
resources than others, but why and how is a mystery. There is a whole area of
“science” dedicated to explaining the world pretending work doesn’t happen,
and it’s called “economy”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a builder makes something, or works on improving it, or pays for something,
they want to own it (or a part of it). You should own the fruits of your work.
You may, and should, give up some of that to cover the costs of infrastructure
or for social security and the like. Taking something by force is a crime. If
you find lost property, you should return it to the owner, possibly for
a prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A politician owns anything they can control and defend. If you can take
something by force and hold on to it, it’s now yours. If you lose control of
something, it’s free for taking for anyone else. Finders keepers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="seeing-each-other"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Seeing Each Other&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politicians view the builders as extremely naive and stupid. They think they
are much smarter and more mature, because they can cheat and trick them. At
the same time they find builders extremely annoying with their insistence on
fairness and owning things they made. They most annoying situation is when the
politics collides with the physical reality, and you absolutely need the
practical worldview to make any sort of progress, so the politicians have to
pander to the builders and pretend to care for what they think, or use
wasteful violence to force them to cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The builders see the politicians as evil and tedious. Their constant squabbles
and feuding gets in the way of getting the work done, and their dishonesty
makes it pretty much impossible to do business with them. The fact that
a politician would rather be a king on a ruin than an prosperous person among
equals makes him look like a selfish asshole. When forced to work with them,
builders will often learn to manage the politicians to keep them busy fighting
each other and away from interfering with important work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="art-and-literature"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Art and Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to pick two genres of literature that show the differences between
the two worldviews, I would pick Fantasy and SciFi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a poor boy who is secretly a prince or otherwise destined to rule
and save the world, who then proves their worth by coming out victorious from
different adventures and challenges, defeats both the evil monsters
threatening the kingdom and any competition, and wins, then you are reading
political story. Not surprisingly, pretty much any legend, saga, tale, play,
or epic are political works. Many were directly commissioned by politicians
as means to achieve political goals, such as fame and immortality. (Did
I mention politician believe themselves to be immortal?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if there is skilled and smart inventor who in his garage
builds an interdimensional gate, explores other worlds, meets and befriends
strange alien creatures, and is in the end fairly rewarded for his work and
risks, you might have an example of a builder literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are exceptions. The books of Terry Pratchett, for example, while using
fantasy tropes, are very much builder literature, speaking about fairness,
decency, cooperation and healthy competition, and yes, the incomprehensibly
evil behavior of some selfish people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also stories that happen is space in the future, but are very much
political in the worldview they present. The entire Warhammer 40k universe is
an example of this. You have knights with swords and lasers, aliens with
pointy ears who use magic, immortal skeleton robots, and priceless artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of movie adaptations of SciFi stores often end up more political than
the original stories, because they are re-interpreted by politicians in the
process of adapting for a movie. Any large endeavor like shooting a movie is
going to be dominated with politicians, especially when there is relatively
little hard contact with physical reality. The entertainment industry is
a paradise for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="good-and-evil"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Good and Evil&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Jane Jacobs noted, those two worldviews come with two mutually incompatible
moral codes. Each of them will look evil from the point of view of the other,
while it will look good and proper from its own point of view. If I’m painting
the political worldview in darker colors than the practical one, it’s because
of my own biases, and the fact that the political worldview seems to be
dominating the world right now in many areas that could maybe benefit more
from a practical approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evil comes from three possible sources. First, as Jane Jacobs noted, when
you try to mix the tenets of the two systems, you often get a monstrous
hybrid. Allow commercial deals in your political world view, and you get
bribes and corruption. Allow violence in your practical worldview, and you get
East India Company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second source is when people disagree about which of the systems should be
applied in a given situation. Take for example the ridiculously high salaries
of company CEOs. From a political point of view, they hold a very important
position, with a lot of responsibility, and so they deserve it. In fact,
making their salary higher makes the entire company look more powerful. Of
course from the practical point of view their contribution to the work of the
company is practically non existent, and often even negative, and they could
be replaced with a very simple spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are things that are evil according to both of those worldviews,
and no amount of reasoning is going to excuse them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where am I going with this? Why am I writing this article at all? Well,
several reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one, I wanted to get it off my chest and write it down, so that I can
refer to it later. Second, it might actually help someone else to understand
some otherwise inexplicable behavior of other people. I know it helps me to
navigate politics-rich minefields, mostly to get away from them as fast as
possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, I think this might be actionable. As I mentioned, maybe I’m biased, but
I think there is too much political thinking and not enough practical approach
in many areas of modern life. Companies move from selling products to
subscriptions, political parties lean to the right increasingly, science and
art seems to rely increasingly on authority, technical communities are invaded
by evangelists and advocates, and there seems to be a general crisis of trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have this hope that the situation could be improved somewhat (or maybe even
a lot) by promoting the practical worldview more, and pushing to use that
worldview in more situations. To “embody” and “ground” the thinking, bringing
it closer to physical reality and verifiable facts. To reject cynicism and
cruelty of the politicians, and embrace the welcoming and trust of the
builders. I think it’s a cultural shift that we need. We need more builder
media, more books, movies, comics, stories, and games that embrace the
practical worldview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-05-09-politics/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Before we were somewhat brutally brought into the loving embrace of the Roman
Catholic Church by our considerate neighbours, my country had its own “pagan”
religion, with its own mythology and traditions. A lot of the traditions
survive in some way, because you can’t tell people they no longer have
a holiday on a given day just because they are worshipping a different god
now, but most information about the beliefs of my ancestors have been
judiciously eradicated by the same people who were at the time responsible for
preserving history – the chroniclers were mostly priests at the time, after
all. Some of it has been reconstructed from mentions in various historical
texts, but there is very little that is certain. Which is a great shame,
because those “primitive” mythologies often were records of knowledge about
the world and its workings, presented in a form that is easy for people to
understand – attitudes and relationships. That’s why gods in them are mostly
humans with special powers connected with the nature. And that “pagan”
mythology could tell us a lot about how the society functioned back then.</summary>
    <published>2025-05-09T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-07-01-automation/</id>
    <title>The Subtle Art of Automation</title>
    <updated>2025-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="the-subtle-art-of-automation"&gt;

&lt;section id="tools"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans are tool-using animals. For a long time it was thought that this is what
distinguishes us from animals, in fact, but of course if you actually pay
attention you will notice that animals are using tools all the time. Yes,
sometimes you can dismiss it as instinctive behavior, as is the fashion, but
sometimes when it comes to corvids, parrots, octopuses and primates, you really
have to admit that they do it intentionally and with full knowledge about the
expected results. Anyways, humans are among tool-using animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we use tools? Sometimes it’s because we are not strong or dexterous
enough to do thing we want to do unaided. Or our nails and teeth are not sharp
enough. Or our sight, hearing, or sense of touch are not good enough. Other
times we could do the thing unaided if we had to, but tools make it easier or
more convenient. Sometimes it’s because we don’t want to risk an injury, or to
get dirty, or we want to avoid other unpleasant sensation. But the reason I
hear given most often is that by using tools we can do the same thing faster,
or at larger scale, or otherwise more efficiently. We can achieve the same (or better) result with less effort. Tools can be a labour-saving device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We say “tools”, but it’s not just tools. They are just easy to talk about them,
because they are tangible, visible things. But it all applies to skills and
techniques as well. To the “technologies”. Consider, for example, waving
baskets. It’s something you do by hand (today we do have machines that can do
it, but let’s assume we are doing it by hand), but you can do it in several
different ways. Coming up with a new way to wave baskets that is somehow
easier, faster, lets you use different materials or produces baskets with
special qualities that the other ways don’t works exactly the same as if you
created a new tool for doing this. So tools are just physical manifestations
of technologies, and it’s the technologies we will be concerned about here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="effort"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Effort&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So do the technologies really save effort? It certainly feels that way, why
would we be using them otherwise? But I think it’s a bit more complicated than
that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the ox-driven plough. On the face of it, it’s a huge improvement about
the humble hoe that it replaced. Yes, the farmer still has to be present to
drive the plough, and it still requires a lot of strength, but a large amount
of that strength is now provided by the animal, and the whole work goes much
faster. So it’s a definitely a huge saving, at least as long as you only look
at this short time when the ploughing is actually happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the ox has to eat too. And it needs a place to stay, and it needs to be
taken care of. And when it gets old or sick, it has to be replaced. So for this
to work in the long run you need a steady supply of oxen. (And I’m not even
saying anything about the effort of the ox.) So a tiny plot of land that acted
as the farmer’s garden and was enough to feed their family now has to become a
considerably sized field, enough to grow food for a herd of oxen and the people
needed to take care of them. And since the oxen need to eat the entire year,
you have to store your crops somehow, and preserve them.  What used to be a
simple shack with a small garden, where some hoe-ing would happen a few times a
year, turns into a small village with several huts, a barn, an enclosure, and
people working around the clock to maintain all that. And don’t even get me
started about fresh water and the smell of ox everywhere. And of course because
you are not storing considerable caches of food, your little village is now
vulnerable to raids and looting (or the more civilized version of it,
taxation), so you need defensive walls, soldiers (or at least militia),
weapons, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at it this way you could easily conclude that the hoe is in fact the
less labor-intensive solution, when considered globally. It only becomes worse
when you assume that you already have all the infrastructure need for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then again, once you have the infrastructure, it enables not just the
plough, but many other technologies as well. You now have milk and meat. And as
much ox shit as you can shake a stick at. You have fortifications and army.
You have a hierarchy to organize and manage it all. You have surplus food to
trade. And so on and so forth. So assuming you want all those additional things
too, on top of replacing the hoe, the plough once again becomes the superior
technology (for some chosen measure).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="transformers"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transformers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if technologies don’t &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; save effort on their own, what do they do
exactly? I like to think of them as transforming one kind of effort into
another kind, potentially better suited for the task at hand, or maybe just
easier to store or move around. If you compare the rather abstract and nebulous
idea of effort to thermodynamic idea of energy, a technology could be like,
say, a solar cell that transforms light into electricity that can be then
easily moved around using wires and stored using batteries. Or a combustion
engine that transforms chemical energy of the fossil fuels into kinetic energy
of a rotating shaft. Of course the similarity is pretty weak, because we don’t
really have a well defined formal theory of effort, like we have a theory of
thermodynamics, but I like to believe that there is some kind of law of
conservation of effort somewhere in there, however fuzzy and approximate it
might be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, technologies let you transform different kinds of effort,
sometimes allowing you to store or move it around. What good is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out that sometimes some kinds of effort are better for a given task
than other kinds. So you can “save effort” by using the kind that is more
efficient for the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And sometimes certain tasks take less effort when they are done at a particular
place and time, or when they are done at scale. Being able to store and move
effort lets you rearrange it into more efficient ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, sometimes you can “outsource” the effort, by taking advantage of
something someone else already did (or will have to do to clean up after you).
Fossil fuels, for example, take advantage of the effort the plants of millions
of years ago spent to turn light into their bodies, and of the effort the
future generations will have to spend to deal with the climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like in thermodynamics, those conversions rarely are free – usually they
take some additional effort, to, say, dig up those fossil fuels, turn them into
a form that is convenient to use, and transport them to the right place. But
with the right arrangements, even with that overhead we can often create
considerable savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="automation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Automation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automation technologies (together with mechanization) are no different in that
regard, except they tend to require much more infrastructure to make things
happen “on their own”. They also come with a myth that “you only need to set it
up once” and they will work forever without expending any further effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice any ongoing process is going to have setup cost and maintenance
cost (and also cleanup cost, which we often forget about). In addition, the
requirements for the output of the process are going to change over time, and
that requires further effort and resources to adjust it to remain useful
(either by changing the process itself, or by adding extra adapting steps).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the trick is to setup that automation in a way that minimizes those ongoing
costs, possibly doing more work up front, or pushing more work to the cleanup
(and hoping we won’t be around anymore when it happens). This is not a given,
and if it’s not done intentionally, we might as well end up with an automated
process that doesn’t in fact save effort, or accomplish other goals that we
wanted to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="goals"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of goals, saving effort is not the only thing technologies can give
us. In fact, sometimes we are ready to actually spend more effort in order to
achieve some of the other goals. What are they? Potentially they are infinite,
but let’s look at some of the most common ones here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="repeatability"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Repeatability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be a goal to have multiple similar things, or it can be just enabling
the further goals like quality control or fine tuning, but automation sure lets
you do things the same exact way, if setup with that in mind. As a side effect,
it also makes it easier to debug!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="quality-control"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Quality Control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to make sure that the things you are making are at least of a certain
quality. But maybe you also want to make sure that the quality is not
unnecessarily high, as it usually costs more. If your process is automated,
then you can easily inspect it, find the parts that have the most impact on
quality and adjust and monitor them. You can even automate additional quality
checks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="fine-tuning"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fine Tuning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait, it’s not just quality. You can fiddle with any feature of the process
this way. The fact that it always happens the same way, except for the parts
you have changed, lets you more easily see what the results of your changes
are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="interchangeability"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Interchangeability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you design your automation right, you can reuse or share parts of it in
different processes. You could also have intermediate stages of the product
shared between several different processes. This lets you both save effort and
be more flexible about your quotas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="scalability"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Scalability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you make a machine do something, then you can often quite easily run the
machine faster, or buy several machines and have them run in parallel. You can
scale your processes this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="economy-of-scale"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Economy of Scale&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you can scale something, you can scale it up to huge amounts and make use
of all those bulk discounts and bulk shipping. More importantly, you can use
bigger machines to make the same thing faster and cheaper by making a lot at a
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="centralization"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Centralization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously if you have big machines doing a lot of work, you want them all in
one place, so that you can keep all the resources and materials close by,
and so that the maintenance is easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="distribution"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Distribution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you don’t have to centralize everything if you don’t want to. Automation
also enables distribution, letting you to have the same machine (or script)
running in many different locations, close to where they are needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, automation can be quite useful and universal tool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where am I going with this? My main point is that automation is not always
about saving effort, and that it doesn’t automatically save effort wherever it
is used. Sometimes it has other goals, and sometimes it actually makes you
spend more effort, especially when you count all the effort that is normally
not visible, because it hides in the infrastructure or has been pushed out onto
the customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, there are certain patterns and arrangements that you can use with
automation tools that work well for achieving a given goal. And there are also
anti-patterns that make automation pointless or even harmful. The trick is in
knowing what you want to do and how to arrange things to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-07-01-automation/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>Humans are tool-using animals. For a long time it was thought that this is what
distinguishes us from animals, in fact, but of course if you actually pay
attention you will notice that animals are using tools all the time. Yes,
sometimes you can dismiss it as instinctive behavior, as is the fashion, but
sometimes when it comes to corvids, parrots, octopuses and primates, you really
have to admit that they do it intentionally and with full knowledge about the
expected results. Anyways, humans are among tool-using animals.</summary>
    <published>2025-07-01T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-07-08-wishes/</id>
    <title>My Tech Wishes for 2025</title>
    <updated>2025-07-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="my-tech-wishes-for-2025"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it’s a bit late in the year for this kind of post, but I have been busy
with other things. In any case, I decided to make it about general technology
related wishes, and not just CircuitPython, but large part of this is going to
be about CircuitPython anyways. Or at least related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="media-transfer-protocol"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Media Transfer Protocol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exposing your microcontroller to the computer it is connected to as a disk
drive is getting really popular now. And it makes a lot of sense too — it doesn’t require you to install any drivers or programs, it easy to understand, and
very convenient. CircuitPython does it too and I love it. But it does introduce
a number of problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You have to use a filesystem that is supported on most operating system, and
with the small sizes you have, it’s usually FAT12, which is not great for
flash wearing off or fragmentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since diskettes are not as common anymore, proprietary operating systems
don’t have their implementations of FAT12 tested as well as other things,
which means there are lots of bugs in MacOS and Windows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tools like virus scanners or disk monitors see those drives as regular disks
and often interact with them in ways that breaks them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can write to the disk only from one side, either through USB, or from
your code on the device, but not both at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of those problems could be trivially solved if we could only use the MTP
protocol instead of exposing the disk as a physical device with USB MSC. MTP
uses commands to manipulate the files, kinda like FTP, instead of writing to
the disk directly, and writes themselves are done by the microcontroller
itself, so it’s easy to use any custom filesystem you want, and to ensure
proper interactions when multiple operations are happening from different
sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is only one problem, and that is iTunes. You see, back when Apple’s flag
product was a music player, they were very jealous about it, and they tried
very hard to “protect” their users from using any other music player. They made
sure their player uses a custom, proprietary protocol for transferring the
music collection, and they also made sure that Apple computers didn’t support
transferring of arbitrary files using MTP. They had a problem in that most
cameras were already using MTP to transfer photos, and their users needed that,
so they made it an exception: you can use MTP on a Mac, but only for
transferring image files, and not any other file. Neat, eh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today you can only find iPads in museums, and iTunes is just a memory in some
boomer nightmares, but the decision they made back then stays. No arbitrary
files with MTP, if you use a Mac, you have to install a special program to use
MTP for anything else than photos. So any microcontroller device that uses MTP
would not work out of the box on Apple products, which means that nobody does
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my wish is for someone at Apple to revise that decision, recognize how
stupid and harmful it was, and remove that stupid limitation from all of their
operating systems, thank you very much. I would also like to see some ready to
use libraries and examples for using MTP, but that will surely come once it’s
usable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="circuitpython-on-ch32v208"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;CircuitPython on CH32V208&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something I would love to do myself, but I’m scared to even start, as
it is a huge amount of work, and just outside of my comfort zone. Basically,
the bluetooth versions of the CH32 chips tend to have a lot of memory for the
bluetooth stack, and that makes it theoretically possible to run CircuitPython
or LUA on them (as long as we don’t need the bluetooth). It’s a nice cheap
chip, and it would be perfect as a replacement for the SAMD21 chips I currently
use for the PewPew devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course porting whole CircuitPython to a new chip is a lot of work, and it’s
something I have never done before, so naturally it’s scary. But people do it,
so it’s definitely possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="voice-synthesis"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Voice Synthesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After my failed attempts to port the SAM voice synthesiser from MicroBit to
CircuitPython, I’m happy to see that someone ported it to MicroPython, but
not as a C library, as I wanted to do, but literally rewrote it in Python.
Now I need to take it and see if it works in CircuitPython as well. Then I can
make my robots speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="servo-controller-on-ch32v003"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Servo Controller on CH32V003&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one I’m actually perfectly capable of finishing on my own, I just need to
find the energy to work on it. I basically want to control 16 servos with good
resolution using PWM signals specified through I2C. I already have the PWM part
working, and there are plenty of examples for I2C slave. It’s just a question
of sitting down and actually writing the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I have it, I can use it in the future versions of FluffBug and WeeBug, and
also a robot for the new small OpenMV board. It would free up 8 pins on the
Xiao, which could then be used for a display or I2S amplifier. It would also
allow for connecting additional servos, for things like arms or moving
features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="led-matrices-on-ch32v003"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;LED Matrices on CH32V003&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have two projects with LED matrices for the CH32V003 that I still need
to program. One is a spectrum analyzer thing, and the hard part is the FFT
code for it (though there are plenty of examples), and the other is a business
card fake PewPew—not really running CircuitPython, but with some of the
PewPew games implemented directly in C and hardcoded in the device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="gif-pendant"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;GIF Pendant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I’m also still working on my GIF pendant project. Now with a round
screen and CH32V208 as the brains. I have a TinyUSB example for USB MSC in
RAM working on it. What I need to figure out how to put the storage on the
internal flash instead, and how to access it from the code to render those
GIF files onto the screen. Again, it’s something I have never done, and there
isn’t much documentation about it around, so it’s a lot of trial and error.
I wish someone who is more knowledgable about TinyUSB and USB MSC could help
me with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s pretty much it for me for 2025. It’s mostly projects I would like
to finish (or would like someone to finish for me), except for that Apple MTP
thing. Will I get any of my wishes come true? We will see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-07-08-wishes/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>I know it’s a bit late in the year for this kind of post, but I have been busy
with other things. In any case, I decided to make it about general technology
related wishes, and not just CircuitPython, but large part of this is going to
be about CircuitPython anyways. Or at least related.</summary>
    <published>2025-07-08T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-11-02-both-sides/</id>
    <title>Programming on Both Sides of Your Brain</title>
    <updated>2025-11-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <content type="html">&lt;section id="programming-on-both-sides-of-your-brain"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of disagreements in software engineering seem to have a deeper background
than mere technical considerations. Should you move fast and break things, or
should you reinvent the wheel? Does it matter how the code looks like when it
does what you want? And what is the purpose of it all in the first place?  I
propose that many of those arguments arise from different people using
different of two possible fixed worldviews in a variety of contexts, which they
assign automatically and mostly unconsciously, in a similar way to how our
brain resolves bistable perceptions. Furthermore, I propose that the ability to
consciously switch between the two worldviews, and the experience needed to
decide which one to use in the given context, are crucial for the work of a
software engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="necker-cube"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Necker Cube&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably the most well known example of bistable perception is the Necker Cube:
a two-dimensional wireframe drawing of a cube, which can be interpreted in two
ways, because it lacks any cues about the depth of the parts of the image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../../_images/necker.png" class="align-center" src="../../_images/necker.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we look at the drawing, we automatically pick one of the possible
interpretations, and it becomes obvious to us that it’s the correct one. It
requires a conscious effort to switch to the other interpretation, and some
people can’t do it at all. The initial choice is based on context cues, such as
lighting and position of the drawing, personal preference, cultural biases, and
possibly some amount of randomness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other examples of bistable (and multistable) perceptions, some even
harder to switch between without training. But I think this one illustrates the
mechanism well enough for our purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="drawing-on-the-right-side-of-the-brain"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Drawing on the Right Side of the Brain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1979 Betty Edwards published a book describing her technique for teaching
drawing. Her idea was based on the theory of how left and right brain
hemispheres are responsible for different ways of perceiving reality, that was
popular at the time. Today we know that the processes responsible for those two
ways are not actually confined to their corresponding hemispheres, but rather
are both whole-brain processes, but the terminology stuck, so you can still
read people referring to the more verbal and analytic way as the left-brain
functions, or L-mode, and the more visual and intuitive way as the right-brain
functions, or R-mode (the hemisphere sides are reversed compared to which sides
of the body they control, because the nerves cross: left hemisphere controls
the right side of the body, and vice versa). This supposedly explains why
left-handed people are more creative, having a more dominant right hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, no matter how that relates to the actual positions of parts of our
brains, and the processes that take place, the technique seems to be working: by
intentionally suppressing the understanding of the different parts of the scene
we can shift our perceptions to seeing how it looks like, so to say, instead of
what it is, and make it easier to re-create the looks on the paper. Whatever
the neurological explanation for it, the trick seems to be working for many
people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might find that this general strategy may work in other areas than drawing
as well. For example, when listening to music, when tasting food and drinks, or
even with more abstract things, like interpreting poetry, or understanding
mathematical proofs. It often feels like switching between focusing on details,
and perceiving the general shape and feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that we often automatically pick the right mode of perception for the
task in similar way to how we pick an interpretation of the Necker cube above,
based on context cues, personal preference, cultural biases, and experience.
And since it’s mostly unconscious, we are often not aware that a choice has
been made, and that a different interpretation is possible, unless we
intentionally expend the effort to consider it. And that becomes easier with
practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="phases-of-software-design-and-development"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Phases of Software Design and Development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever tried to design a user interface while at the same time writing
code for the back-end, you might have noticed that it’s very difficult to make
it work the way the users expect, instead of mirroring the internal
representation. This is why those tasks are often separated, performed at
different times, if not by completely different members of the team, or even
different teams. There can be many more such phases, where you need to focus
on different aspects of the product, consider different trade-offs, and focus
on different levels of abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe this is, at least partially, because those tasks are best solved in
different perception modes, and we can only be in one of those modes at a time,
just like we can only see one interpretation of the Necker cube at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while there may be a big variety of roles and phases, depending on the
organization and methodology and the task at hand, you might notice that the
worst disagreements usually happen between pairs of roles that can be roughly
divided into two families, roughly corresponding to the L-mode and R-mode from
Betty Edwards’ book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="programming-on-the-left-side-of-the-brain"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Programming on the Left Side of the Brain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The L-mode generally sounds like your stereotypical science nerd. You write
code because you enjoy the difficulty of doing it. You care about the
correctness of your solution not because it will have some business purpose,
but because an incorrect solution would be wrong. You want your code to be
good, whatever it means in the context. You know that either something is true,
or it isn’t, and the only way to tell is through contact with the harsh
reality. You trust your co-workers, and cooperate without friction, unless
someone breaks that trust repeatedly – then you simply start avoiding that
person and working around them. You very carefully pick your tools and
dependencies, and you like to understand how they work before you use them. You
don’t like overcomplicated libraries that do much more than you need. If you
see something that isn’t right, you will try to fix it yourself, and if that is
not possible, you will avoid using it. You believe position should be earned
through work, and trust should be earned trough repeated interactions. You
don’t care much about authorities, and you don’t believe something is right
just because someone says so. You tend to avoid taking sides, and you just want
things to work. You prefer to just show things over describing them. You are
generally quiet, and you prefer to results speak for you. You are generally
an optimist, and you believe in improving things for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="programming-on-the-right-side-of-the-brain"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Programming on the Right Side of the Brain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The R-mode is more like a salesman. You don’t really care about how the thing
is done, as long as everyone agrees that it works. If someone disagrees, you
may fix it by changing how it works, or by convincing that person that they are
wrong, either way is fine, as long as there is a consensus. People who believe
in inviolate truths just don’t have a flexible mind. You love workarounds and
temporary solutions. You juggle technical debt like a government economist.
You take sides and stick to them, because position and trust is achieved
through loyalty or authority enforcement. You like procedures and processes,
even if they don’t work – after all it’s not your fault it doesn’t work when
you followed the process correctly. You have friends and enemies among your
co-workers, but it changes all the time, depending on what you need and who has
what to offer. You love powerful and complicated tools and libraries,
especially when they are popular – after all, nobody was fired for choosing
IBM. You are sensitive to fashions and trends, and you always try to work on
the coolest projects. Your favorite mode of communication is telling stories.
You are generally a fatalist, and you believe in making the best use of what is
available to you right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="switching-contexts"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Switching Contexts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above descriptions are very stereotypical. In reality, to survive in the
modern world, everyone one of us, even the most nerdy nerds and the most
popular celebrities, have to switch between those modes. Doing grocery
shopping?  You need the L-mode. Deciding what to have for lunch? That’s R-mode.
And we often don’t even realize we switch those modes, because it happens
mostly automatically, depending on the context. Unless sometimes it doesn’t,
and we are stuck in the wrong mode for the task at hand. This can happen for a
variety of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people simply prefer one mode over the other, because of their
personality, neural makeup, or cultural biases. For example, autistic people
generally tend to prefer the L-mode, while people with authoritarian
personality traits will lean towards the R-mode more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your training and experience might tell you that a certain mode works better in
the given situation, while someone who was trained for a different profession,
or even just by different methodology, will disagree with you, not only about
what mode is more appropriate, but even what the situation actually is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have locked on to a specific mode at a certain time in the project,
and in the mean time the situation may have changed, so a person joining later
will choose a different one. Or you might have noticed the change and switched
your mode, while your colleagues didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if the task at hand is novel, you might simply not know which mode to
choose, and may pick it at random.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the cause, when two people are in different modes in the same context
it’s very difficult for them to agree about anything. And since the mode
switching is normally completely unconscious and automatic, and because the
mode you are in always feels the only obvious one for the situation, it feels
like a perfectly normal, smart and reasonable person suddenly disagrees with
you about the most fundamental and common sense things. It’s very frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course even when you realize that you have a mode mismatch, it’s not trivial
to decide which mode is more appropriate for the given context, or even where
the boundaries at which it should be switched lie. Whichever mode you are at
the moment, it feels like the obviously right one for you, and since they
differ in how values are assessed, it may be hard to decide which one was more
appropriate even in hindsight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="elasticity-and-training"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Elasticity and Training&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that people who can switch between the two modes easily are
generally more successful at software engineering jobs (and many others too).
Obviously it’s not enough to be able to switch, but also to know when to do it,
and that comes with experience, but if you generally are reluctant to switch,
you are more likely to be in the wrong mode at the wrong time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the right training for the job helps with the experience part. And that
is often hands-on training, and not theoretical knowledge read in a book,
because the context picking and mode switching is mostly automatic, based
on unconsciously picked cues, that a book would not communicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dividing the project into phases and the team into roles at the right places
helps with switching to the right modes as well, by making the boundaries of
the different context explicitly visible, so a conscious effort can be made
by the team members to get into the right mode for the particular phase and
their role in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the different roles often requiring different modes, there is no way to
completely avoid conflict inside the team. This is in fact the main reason to
have the roles in the first place – to catch problems visible in either of the
modes. It’s important to realize that those differences are often
irreconcilable – the differences between how the world is seen in the two
modes makes it impossible to form a consensus, and some other way of conflict
resolution is necessary. In the end it might be just necessary to agree to
disagree. For this reason it’s important for the different phases and roles to
have distinct, non-overlapping areas of responsibility, so that in the case of
irreconcilable disagreement it is known whose decision is final.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my hypothesis of the two distinct mental modes in software engineering
work is completely made up and unsubstantiated, and based entirely on anecdotal evidence, I am confident that it provides a useful tool for understanding the
behavior of teams, and may help in organizing projects in a way that reduces
conflict and improves performance. I have absolutely no proof of that beyond
my feelings about this. The reader is advised to use their own judgement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="http://dopieralski.pl/posts/2025-11-02-both-sides/" rel="alternate"/>
    <summary>A lot of disagreements in software engineering seem to have a deeper background
than mere technical considerations. Should you move fast and break things, or
should you reinvent the wheel? Does it matter how the code looks like when it
does what you want? And what is the purpose of it all in the first place?  I
propose that many of those arguments arise from different people using
different of two possible fixed worldviews in a variety of contexts, which they
assign automatically and mostly unconsciously, in a similar way to how our
brain resolves bistable perceptions. Furthermore, I propose that the ability to
consciously switch between the two worldviews, and the experience needed to
decide which one to use in the given context, are crucial for the work of a
software engineer.</summary>
    <published>2025-11-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
